Speaker: ‘One day I’d like to do a big adventure.’
I hear this all the time, at parties, at events I speak at, by email from strangers.
‘But I don’t have the time / money / fitness / shiny kit.’
The excuses vary occasionally, but the essence remains the same:
‘One day I want adventure in my life, but, unfortunately, it can’t be right now’.
Waiting for all your stars to align is a guaranteed way to ensure
that the adventure you crave will never happen.
Waiting until you somehow, suddenly and simultaneously,
have both loads of money and plenty of time is daft
(if you’ll excuse me being a bit direct before we have got to know one another properly).
One day! What rubbish!
If this applies to you, listen! You do not need a winning lottery ticket to have an adventure.
What you need is a polite kick up the backside! A push.
I want this book to give you the tiny bit of momentum needed to get started.
This is a book for people who want adventure in their life,
but find that real life has got in the way.
‘One day’ is just an excuse. It’s lazy, self-deluding and – worst of all – completely unnecessary.
So if you are procrastinating and dithering about committing to adventure,
why don’t you begin with a one-day adventure,
something so tiny that it can barely be called an adventure?
Let’s call it a ‘microadventure’. Now go and do it as soon as you can, not ‘one day’...
Tomorrow would be a good time to start. Or this weekend at the very latest. Start small.
But do start.
The concept is simple: Pick up your wallet. You’re ready.
Open the door, step out…and begin.
(This sentence, by the way, is the hardest thing you will read in this entire book.)
Then jump on a train. I’d suggest doing this microadventure by bike,
because you can explore so much more new ground that way,
but going by foot is a simple alternative. Hell, take a canoe if you like.
Anyway, choose a station, almost at random, that’s about 30 miles away from your home.
Buy a one-way ticket.
I say 30 miles because it’s a distance long enough to be challenging on a bike,
but achievable in one day, even if you are pretty unfit.
If you’re on foot or if you can’t manage 30 miles, then do a shorter trip.
But don’t just duck out and do no trip! This approach applies throughout this book:
if something I suggest is too difficult, do an easier version.
If something is too easy, make it harder. Mould it and adapt it to your own situation.
Just make sure you do something.
When you arrive at your destination, hop on your bike and cycle home.
Travelling 30 miles away from your home should guarantee
that you’ll begin the adventure in lovely countryside.
I suggest you navigate homewards using a compass,
or the Crowsflight app on your smartphone, rather than a map.
A compass (or the app) won’t tell you what route to take,
it will only point you in the right direction.
The twists and turns and decisions that crop up along the way are
therefore down to your instinct and serendipity.
It becomes more of a journey into the unknown
than merely following the clearly prescribed route back home that a map would give you.
If that feels a bit daunting, by all means use a map or even a satnav.
Don’t let any of the ideas in this book put you off! Just modify them to what appeals to you.
I once spent four years cycling back home.
Within the single day ahead of you will lie most of the challenges, hurdles and rewards,
of a multi-year ride – although maybe fewer bears. But I mean this seriously.
You will have to navigate your way,
you’ll become wildly hungry and relish the joy of stopping at a café and eating cake, guilt free.
You will see things you have never seen before.
If you travel slowly and with a smile on your face, then you will meet different people,
have interesting conversations and learn something new about the world and about yourself.
When you eventually make it back to your front door, you’ll be tired, aching, and hungry.
But you will have had an unusual and rewarding day and – I sincerely hope
– you will have realized that you are capable of more and are thus eager for more.
You have opened the door to adventure.